Dereck Katuli

Curriculum Vitae

C/O Mr. R. Katuli, Box 2381, Blantyre

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/dereck-katuli-057b14171/

Personal Details:

Place/Date of Birth: Blantyre, 29th December 1995 Home of Origin: Blantyre District T.A. Kapeni

Gender: Male Marital Status: Single

Personal Profile

Skilled data enthusiast with 3+ years of experience in collecting, organizing, interpreting and disseminating various types of statistical figures. Reliable presenter and self-assured communicator with the ability to circulate information in a way that is concise, efficient and beneficial for end users. I am creative when it comes to finding solutions to problems and determining modifications for optimal use of organizational data. Expert in data mining, statistical analysis and business intelligence gathering and benchmarking. Organized and timely in providing staff, departmental members and executive management with reports on specific data findings and their impact on organization growth and success.

Experience

December 2022 to Present – Global Health Informatics Institute.

Data Analyst

- Data Quality and Assurance

- o Developing data quality metrics and standards for different types of data.
- Developing data quality models to identify issues with the data and recommending solutions to improve data quality.
- Reviewing data quality protocols, procedures and policies to ensure compliance with industry standards.
- Conducting data quality audits to identify any issues with accuracy, completeness, and consistency of data within databases.
- Recommending data quality solutions (automating manual processes or developing a new application)
- o to handle data more efficiently.
- Monitoring the quality of incoming data to identify any errors or inconsistencies that may need to be corrected.
- o Creating reports that detail the quality of data within the databases.
- Developing data quality training programs for employees who have access to sensitive data.

- Data Request Handling

- Set expectations about the data requests workflow with reasonable timelines in line with the SOPs.
- o Define data requests workflow.
- o Record/ track all data requests.
- Automate repetitive data requests.
- Measure and improve the data requests workflow by getting feedback from the stakeholders.

- Stakeholder reports and visualization.

 Prepare reports based on stakeholder indicators on time and if necessary stating trends, patterns, and predictions using relevant data.

- o Prepare final analysis reports for stakeholders to understand the data-analysis steps enabling data-driven decisions.
- o Understand data storage and data sharing methods, identify, analyze and interpret trends or patterns in complex datasets.
- o Convert or visualize data into usable information that is easy to understand using different tools to suit the relevant stakeholders.

- Other duties

- Work with engineers and leads to identify process improvement opportunities, proposed modifications and new process improvement opportunities.
- o Training end-users on new reports and dashboards.
- o Researching solutions to overcome data analytics challenges.
- o Involved in increasing data use activities among stakeholders.
- Any other duties assigned from time to time.

February 2020 to December 2022 – Telekom Networks Malawi (TNM)

BI and Analytics Specialist

- Facilitating PORI reconciliations and providing monthly dealer incentives reports.
- Ensuring that dealer's PORI performance daily updates are up to date.
- Ensuring timely provision of adhoc reports to various stakeholders.
- Daily monitoring of Qlik monitoring app.
- Ensuring all files are loaded in time for reporting and monitoring daily CDR reconciliations.
 Ensuring all reporting and BI systems are available by monitoring disk space and table space on reporting servers.
- Data partition and retention management.
- Developing backup scripts for all data loading and reporting scripts.
- Developing CBS data loaders
- Developing adhoc scripts for pulling data from Gauss DB.
- Drive improved data driven decisions to target various aspects of the business.
- Ensuring efficient ETL of data from various data sources into staging area.

Data Analyst,

- Facilitating PORI reconciliations and providing monthly dealer incentives reports.
- Ensuring that dealer's PORI performance daily updates are up to date.
- Ensuring timely provision of adhoc reports to various stakeholders.
- Daily monitoring of Qlik monitoring app.
- Ensuring all files are loaded in time for reporting and monitoring daily CDR reconciliations. Ensuring all reporting and BI systems are available by monitoring disk space and table space on reporting servers.
- Data partition and retention management.
- Developing backup scripts for all data loading and reporting scripts.
- Developing CBS data loaders.

Graduate Trainee,

- Ensuring timely provision of adhoc reports to various stakeholders.
- Daily monitoring of Qlik monitoring app.
- Ensuring all files are loaded by monitoring daily CDR reconciliations app.
- Daily monitoring of disk space and table space on reporting servers.

Systems Proficiency

Operating Systems: Windows 10, Linux.

DBMS: Oracle 11g, PostgreSQL, MySQL, Gauss DB.

Programming Languages and Scripting: PHP, Python, Shell Scripting.

Reporting Tools: Excel, Qlik Sense, Metabase.

Education

2015 – 2019 – BSc in Information and Communication Technology (Mzuzu University) 2009 – 2013 - Malawi Schools Certificate of Education at Michiru View Boys Secondary School

Natural Languages: English and Chichewa

Referees

James Mandiza, BI & Reporting Manager, TNM james.mandiza@tnm.co.mw
 Noordeen Malango, Business Analyst, FCB noordinmalango@gmail.com

Steve Chanza, IT & Innovations Manager, PCL <u>chanzasteve@gmail.com</u>